

RESEARCH SCIENTIST · RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSIC

Department of Physics, 1110 West Green Street, Urbana, Illinois, 61801-3003, US

□ (+217) 819-9458 | ☑ ruizm@illinois.edu | 🎓 miltonruizm.github.io

### **Summary** \_

Research Scientist in the Department of Physics at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign studying compact objects mergers in magnetized environments, including binary black holes in gaseous disks, black hole–neutron star, neutron star binaries, and exotic objects such as ergostars. The goal of my research is to predict and correlate observable gravitational-waves and electromagnetic signatures from these events. Also, strongly interested in alternative theories of gravity and mathematical aspects of numerical relativity.

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Research Scientist Urbana, Illinois

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS,

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

Aug 2016-

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Urbana, Illinois

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS,

UIUC 2013 - 2016

CPAN Postdoctoral Research Associate

Palma de Mallorca, Spain

SPANISH NATIONAL CENTER FOR PARTICLE, ASTROPARTICLE AND NUCLEAR PHYSICS,

Universitat de les Illes Balears 2011 - 2013

Postdoctoral Research Associate Jena, Germany

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT,

Friedrich-Schiller-Universität 2009 - 2010

### Education

Ph.D. Physics Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL AUTONOMOUS UNIVERSITY OF MEXICO (UNAM)

• Dissertation: Axial symmetry, Gravitational Waves and Boundary Conditions

Advisor: Miguel Alcubierre Field: Numerical Relativity

Master of Science (Physics)

Mexico City, Mexico

UNAM

Bachelor of Science (Physics)

Bogota, Colombia

NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

June, 2003

• Dissertation: Exact Solution of the Einstein's Equations

# **Major Collaborations**.

#### **CONACYT Thematic Network:**

Black Holes & Gravitational Waves

*México, México* 2017 -2019

April, 2009

June, 2006

LISA Consortium:

Numerical Relativity & Analytical Relativity – Waveform modeling for MBHBs group

Urbana, Illinois

July 2018 –

### **Honors & Awards**

2015-2016 **Fellowship for Basic Research**, Colombian Ministry of Education
2011-2013 **Fellowship for advance research**, Spanish National Center for Astroparticle and Nuclear Physics
2005-2009 **Fellowship for PhD studies**, Mexican Ministry of Education
2000-2004 **Fellowship for B.S. studies**, Colombian Ministry of Education

Bogota, Colombia Madrid, Spain Mexico City, Mexico Bogota, Colombia

### **Research Stays**.

Friedrich-Schiller-Universität
Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut

Jena, Germany

June-July 2008

**Louisiana State University** 

Louisiana, US

CENTER FOR COMPUTATIONAL AND TECHNOLOGY

June - Aug 2006

## **Teaching Experience**

**Guest Lecturer** 

Graduate level

INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER

Bucaramanga, Colombia, 2015

· Lecture: Advanced Topics in General Relativity

**Teaching Assistant** 

Undergraduate level

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut, Friedrich-Schiller-Universität

• Lecture: Numerische Relativitaetstheorie (Numerical Relativity)

Jena, Germany, 2010

#### **Teaching Assistant**

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT, FRIEDRICH-SCHILLER-UNIVERSITÄT

• Lecture: Allgemeine Relativitaetstheorie (General Relativity)

Undergraduate level

Jena, Germany, 2009

Undergraduate level

#### Teaching Assistant/Grader

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico, 2006-2007

• Lecture: General Relativity

Teaching Assistant/Grader
DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

Graduate level

• Lecture: Classical Mechanics

Graduate level

Teaching Assistant/Grader
DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

#### • Lecture: Quantum Mechanics

### **Student Advising**

 $2016\text{-}2018 \; \textbf{Abid Khan, graduate student}, \, \textbf{UIUC}$ 

Urbana, Illinois

2015 - Lunan Sun, graduate student, UIUC

Urbana, Illinois

2018 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Guangkuo Liu, Minh Nguyen, Kyle Nelli, UIUC

Urbana, Illinois

2019 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Samuel Qunell, Michael Mudd, UIUC

Urbana, Illinois

# Seminar and Conference Organizer \_\_\_\_\_

#### **Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar**

WEEKLY SEMINAR

Urbana, Illinois

Jan 2017 - Dec 2017

#### **First Symposium of Relativistic Astrophysics**

INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER

Bucaramanga, Colombia

June 10-12, 2015

DECEMBER 14, 2020 MILTON RUIZ · CURRICULUM

#### **Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar**

WEEKLY SEMINAR

*Urbana, Illinois*Aug 2013 - May 2014

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Journal Club

WEEKLY SEMINAR

Urbana, Illinois

2013-2015

# **Grants/Allocations\_**

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

CO-PI, HIGH-END COMPUTING RESOURCES NASA (\$2057)

*Awarded: 4,291,380 SBUs* 2018-2021

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

Co-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Awarded: 3,404,828.0 SUs

"Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 750,000 node-hours (\$ 465,500 USD)

2018-2019

**Black Hole Formation on Cosmological Space-times** 

PI, INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER/COLCIENCIAS

Awarded: \$ 16,500 USD 2014-2015

**Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers** 

Co-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 500,000 node-hours

2017-2018

Studies In Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

Co-PI, RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Awarded: 3,000,000 SUs (\$145,539.34 USD)

2017-2018

Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 990,000 node-hours

2016-2017

Compact Object Binary Mergers: Simulations in Full General Relativity

Co-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (PHY100053)

Awarded 4,069,156 SUs (\$145,539.34 USD)

2014-2015

Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 610,000 node-hours

2013-2014

**Electromagnetic Signatures of Neutron Star Binaries** 

PI, MARE NOSTRUM BSC ALLOCATION (FI-2011-3-0017)

Awarded: 120,000 core-hours (\$18,895.45 €)

2011-2012

# Peer Reviewer/Referee

- · Classical and Quantum Gravity
- Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society
- Physical Review D
- Physical Review Letters
- The Astrophysical Journal

**Invited Talks/Panelist** 

Stellar compact mergers as progenitors of gravitational waves & short-gamma ray bursts

Online seminar at Mathematics and Physics Department of Aveiro University

Aveiro, Portugal

Dec 9, 2020

Black hole-neutron star and binary neutrons star mergers: Progenitors of sGRBs

TCAN ON BINARY NEUTRON STAR WORKSHOP

Rocher institute of technology, Rochester, NY, US

July 7-10, 2020

**Community Astrophysics Science with the Einstein Toolkit Code** 

University of Guadalajara

Guadalajara, Mx Nov 20-24, 2017

Multimessenger astronomy: The new era of gravitational waves and electromagnetic

Signatures

COLLABORATIVE CONFERENCE ON GRAVITATIONAL WAVES

Jeju, Korea

May 22-26, 2017

Gravitational Waves, a New Observational Window on the Universe

PHYSICS COLLOQUIUM, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col May 16-19, 2016

Nov 4-6, 2015

Numerical relativity at the University of Santander

CELEBRATING ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF THE GENERAL RELATIVITY

Barranquilla, Col

Numerical Solutions of the Einstein's field Equations

Bucaramanga, Col

FIRST SYMPOSIUM ON RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSICS

June 10-12, 2015

The Cactus code and Numerical Relativity

NATIONAL ASTRONOMICAL OBSERVATORY, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col

Dec 16-20, 2006

**Contributed Talks** 

Black hole-neutron star and binary neutrons star mergers: Progenitors of sGRBs

30TH ANNUAL MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

University of Notre Dame, IN, US

Oct 21-23, 2020

Spinning binary neutron star mergers: Effects of the spin on jet outflows

29TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Allendale, Michigan, US

Oct 4-5, 2019

Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching

APS APRIL MEETING

Denver, Colorado, US

April 13-16, 2019

GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Maximum Mass

28TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Wisconsin-Milwaukee, US

Oct 12-13, 2018

Accretion Disks Around Supermassive Binary Black Holes: GRMHD Simulations of

Postdecoupling and Merger
12TH INTERNATIONAL LISA SYMPOSIUM

Chicago, Il, US

July 8-13, 2018

GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star

Maximum Mass
APS APRIL MEETING

Columbus, Ohio, US

April 14-17, 2018

GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets

27TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Ann Arbor, Michigan, US

Oct 12-14, 2017

Binary neutron star mergers as engines of short gamma-ray bursts: delayed vs. prompt collapse

APS APRIL MEETING

Washington, DC, US

Jan 28-31, 2017

MHD simulations of NSNS mergers in full GR: the role of the initial B field on the emergence of sGRB jets

APS APRIL MEETING

Salt Lake City, Utah, US

April 16-19, 2016

Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges

25TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

*Evanston, II, US Oct 1-3, 2015* 

**Numerical Relativity: From Vacuum to Matter Spacetimes** 

Black Hole-Neutron Star Coalescence as engines that power sGRBs

THE 1ST COLOMBIA-ICRANET JULIO GARAVITO ARMERO MEETING

Bogotá-Bucaramanga, Col

Bogotá, Col

Nov 23-27, 2015

SECOND WORKSHOP ON ASTRONOMY

July 27-31, 2015

Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges II

APS APRIL MEETING

Baltimore, Maryland, US

April 11-14, 2015

Gravitational Waves as Probes of Dark Matter Spikes around Massive Black Holes

THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR

Urbana, Il, US

Sep 3, 2014

General relativistic corrections to the pulsar spin-down luminosity

APS APRIL MEETING

Savannah, Georgia

April 5-8, 2014

I-Love-Q Relations in Neutron Stars and their Applications to Astrophysics, Gravitational Waves and Fundamental Physics

THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR

Urbana, Il, US

Feb 2, 2014

Initial boundary value problem of the Z4c formulation of General Relativity

23TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Evanston, Il, US

Oct 25-26, 2013

The Initial Value Problem in General Relativity

CoCoNuT MEETING

Palma de Mallorca, Spain

Nov 26-28, 2012

High Order Outer Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation

WORKSHOP ON NUMERICAL AND MATHEMATICAL RELATIVITY

Oppurg, Germany

Oct 11-13, 2012

Magnetospheres of compact objects in Force-Free Plasma

2ND IBERIAN GRAVITATIONAL WAVE MEETING

WORKSHOP ON COMPUTATIONAL GENERAL RELATIVITY

Barcelona, Spain Feb 15-17, 2012

Province, Rhode Island, US

**Constraint Preserving Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation** 

May 20-22, 2011

Constraint Preserving Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation of General Relativity

19TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON GENERAL RELATIVITY AND GRAVITATION

Mexico City, Mx

Oct 25-27, 2010

### Refereed Publications

Black hole-neutron star coalescence: effects of the neutron star spin on jet launching and dynamical ejecta mass

M. Ruiz, V. Paschalidis, A. Tsokaros, S. L. Shapiro

Phys. Rev. D in press ArXiv:2011.08863

2020

Gravitational Waves from Disks Around Spinning Black Holes: Simulations in Full General ArXiv:2011 04077 Relativity Submitted to PRD E. WESSEL, V. PASCHALIDIS, A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2020 Magnetic Ergostars, Jet Formation and Gamma-Ray Bursts: Ergoregions versus Horizons Phys. Rev. D 102, 104022 M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, S. L. SHAPIRO, KYLE NELLI, SAM QUELL 2020 GW190814: Spin and equation of state of a neutron star companion Astrophys. J. 905, 48 A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2020 Ergostar models: where do they reside? Phys. Rev. D 101, 064069 A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2020 **Prospects for Fundamental Physics with LISA** Gen. Rel. Grav. 52, 81 E. BARAUSSE ET AL. Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations of Binary Neutron Star Mergers in General Relativity: Phys. Rev. D 101, 064042 **Effects of Magnetic Field Orientation on Jet Launching** M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, S. L. SHAPIRO 2020 The great impostors: Extremely compact, merging binary neutron stars in the mass gap Phys. Rev. Lett. 124, 071101 posing as binary black holes A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, L. Sun, S. L. Shapiro, K. Uryu 2019 Dynamically stable ergostars exist: General relativistic models and simulations Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, 231103 A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, L. Sun, S. L. Shapiro, K. Uryu Enabling real-time multi-messenger astrophysics discoveries with deep learning Nature Reviews Physics 1, 600 E. HUERTA ET AL. 2019 Effect of spin on the inspiral of binary neutron stars Phys.Rev. D100, 024061 A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, K. URYU Are fast radio bursts the most likely electromagnetic counterpart of neutron star mergers Phys. Rev. D100, 043001 resulting in prompt collapse? V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz 2019 Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching Phys.Rev. D99, 084032 M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, K. URYU Magnetic Braking and Damping of Differential Rotation in Massive Stars Phys.Rev. D99, 064057 L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2019 Constant circulation sequences of binary neutron stars and their spin characterization Phys. Rev. D98, 124019 A. TSOKAROS, K. URYU, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2018 Jet launching from binary black hole-neutron star mergers: Dependence on black hole Phys. Rev. D98, 123017 spin, binary mass ratio and magnetic field orientation M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, S. L. SHAPIRO 2018 Simulating the Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Incorporating Gas Phys. Rev. D98, 103008 **Pressure Perturbations and Different Rotation Profiles** L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2018 Disks Around Merging Binary Black Holes: From GW150914 to Supermassive Black Holes Phys. Rev. D97, 044036 A. Khan, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2018 GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Phys. Rev. D 97, 021501R Maximum Mass M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, A. Tsokaros 2018 The initial boundary value problem for free-evolution formulations of General Relativity Class. Quan. Grav. 35 015006 D. HILDITCH, M. Ruiz GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets Phys. Rev. D 96, 084063 M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2017 Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Black Hole Formation, Gravitational Phys. Rev. D 96, 043006 **Waves and Jets** L. Sun, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro 2017 Gravitational wave content and stability of uniformly, rotating, triaxial neutron stars in Phys. Rev. D 95, 124057 general relativity T. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, L. BAIOTTI, K. URYU 2017 Binary neutron star mergers: a jet engine for short gamma-ray bursts Astrophys. J. Lett. 824, L6 M. Ruiz, R. Lang, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro 2016 Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges Astrophys. J. Lett. 806, L14 V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz, S. L. SHAPIRO 2015 Accretion disks around binary black holes of unequal mass: GRMHD simulations of Phys. Rev. D 90, 104030 postdecoupling and merger R. Gold, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, Z. B. Etienne, H. Pfeiffer The Pulsar spin-down luminosity: simulations in general relativity Phys. Rev. D 89, 084045 M. Ruiz, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro Almost-Killing conserved currents: a general mass function Phys. Rev. D 89, 025011 M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, C. Bona. Induced scalarization in boson stars and scalar gravitational radiation Phys. Rev. D 86, 104044 M. Ruiz, J. C. DEGOLLADO, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ, M. SALGADO 2012 The role of the ergosphere in the Blandford-Znajek process Mon. Not. R. Aston. Soc. 423 M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, F. Galeazzi, C. Bona. 2012 Constraint preserving boundary conditions for the Z4c formulation of general relativity Phys. Rev. D 83, 024025 M. Ruiz, D. HILDITCH, S. BERNUZZI 2011 Dynamic transition to spontaneous scalarization in boson stars Phys. Rev. D 81, 124018 M. Alcubierre J. C. Degollado, D. Nunez, M. Ruiz, M. Salgado 2010 Multipole expansions for energy and momenta carried by gravitational waves Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 2467 M. Ruiz, M. Alcubierre, D. Nunez, R. Takahashi 2008

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric evolution codes in numerical relativity

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

M. Ruiz, O. RINNE, O. SARBACH

Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 159

2008

Outer boundary conditions for Einstein's field equations in harmonic coordinates

Class. Quant. Grav. 24, 6349

2007

Conference Publications

Gravity and Light: Combining Gravitational Wave and Electromagnetic Observations in the 2020s

FERMILAB-PUB-19-169-AE

R. FOLEY ET AL.

2019

Deep Learning for Multi-Messenger Astrophysics: A Gateway for Discovery in the Big Data

arXiv:1902.00522

G. ALLEN ET AL.

2019

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric codes in numerical relativity

Rev. Mex. Fis. 53, 144

2007

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

Computer Skills \_\_\_\_\_

Operating Systems: UNIX, Linux, Windows, Mac OS X

Programming Language: FORTRAN, C, C++

Graphics and Image Processing: Mathematica, Microcal Origin, SM, Gnuplot, VIsIt, Python

Document Preparation LaTeX, Microsoft Office, Open/Libre Office

Other: Bash scripting, Basic system administration

Languages \_\_\_\_\_

**Spanish (native speaker)** 

**English** 

# Primary References \_\_\_\_\_

### **Professor Miguel Alcubierre**

Departamento de Gravitación y Teoría de Campos Instituto de Ciencias Nucleares UNAM Mexico City, Mexico malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx +55 562-33-371 Ext. 3371

### Professor Sebastiano Bernuzzi

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut Friedrich-Schiller-Universitaät Jena Jena, Germany sebastiano.bernuzzi@uni-jena.de +49 (0)3641 9 47111

### **Professor Vasileios Paschalidis**

Astronomy and Physics Departments University of Arizona Tucson, Arizona, US vpaschal@email.arizona.edu +1 520-621-9643

### **Professor Stuart L. Shapiro**

Department of Physics University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Urbana, Il, US slshapir@illinois.edu +1 217-333-5427